I've been getting asked a lot lately
about my thoughts about the future of
software development whenever a new AI
Advance is released I get a flood of
questions asking what is the future for
software developers and I think the
question they are not asking is will I
still be allowed to code in the future
obviously everything besides c will
still be legal I I feel like the real
question that they're asking is will I
still be able to get paid with the
skills that I'm learning while I learn
to code and so the first thing I want to
say is I hate predicting things
particularly in public if you would have
asked me 5 years ago about if any of
this AI Tech if we would have it today
I'm pretty sure I would have said no and
I'm not talking about the crazy hyped up
demos I'm talking conversational AI that
returns some semblance of a conversation
even if it's mostly hallucinated I I I
don't think I wasn't thinking that was
going to be possible so I've had to
update my priors many times throughout
the last few years regarding Ai and its
capabilities and therefore it's future
capabilities as well so I just don't
have enough hubris to think that I know
what's going to happen in the future I
guess I do have just enough huis though
to post this video about my thoughts so
there's two major points though that I
want to talk about the first is that I
think software is more than coding and
then the second is that programming
itself is more than coding
and before I sort of go deep on those I
want to just seed for the sake of
argument that AI will be able to do
coding tasks that a junior engineer is
currently exposed to do AI will be able
to perform these as faster faster and
more cheaply than those Junior engineers
and AI will be able to do this and
productionize right sort of rolled out
to people um sometime in say the next 5
years I realize some people in my chat
keep telling me that this is going to be
in 6 months but that roll out SC seems
quite difficult to change the entire
structure of an industry in that time
but that's a conversation for a separate
video the reason I say that is because I
don't want to fight about what I think
the particular capabilities of AI are
going to be instead I want to talk about
that with sort of that scenario in mind
and if you think any of those points are
much too aggressive in favor of AI then
that's totally fine my argument will
just be bolstered in my in my corner the
other clarification I want to make is
for the rest of the video when I say
coding I'm sort of referring to this act
of sitting in front of a computer typing
autocom completing copying pasting a
programming language into an editor and
then shipping that to prod in some sense
the exclusively physical act of creating
software so when I say software is more
than coding what do I mean I'm saying
people don't pay for code they
definitely don't pay to just watch you
code unless you're a twitch streamer I
guess then people like doing that that
but what they pay for is for problems to
be solved and when you're coding you're
not getting paid for that code you're
getting paid to solve somebody else's
problems real or perceived these
problems might be for a client or they
could be for your boss or they could be
even for other software developers right
but the reason you're getting paid is
because the problem you're solving for
someone is valuable enough for them to
part with their beloved cash this boils
down to software being able to maybe
provide something that's faster or
cheaper or more reliable than what could
have been accomplished
previously and software is a super set
of just those coding tasks of just
literally typing into the computer
because you need more than just good
algorithms or a nice type system to
create value for your customers not to
say those aren't important just I'm
saying there is more to software than
that you need to be able to understand
requirements and update them when things
change this may even involve a hesitate
to say it talking to a client or to a
stakeholder you need to be able to
practice communication understanding the
non- technical aspects communicated to
you sometimes called listening in the
area of someone else's expertise and you
also need to be able to communicate
technical Concepts to non-technical
people in your area of expertise you
need to be able to say no to feature
creep and scope management your project
can't do everything right you need to be
able to say noce something you'd like to
do but think the cost is more than what
it's worth like maybe rewriting your
front end in Rust there's social aspects
to software and to making software like
listening to feedback and giving
constructive feedback there is mentoring
and being mentored there's patience
kindness and respect all of these things
create teams that are generally seeming
to be more effective at creating
software and there's also asking and
understanding things like how do we make
money at this company the best software
developers I've ever worked at were
great at all of these including coding
they definitely were great at writing
code but they understood each of these
and helped me to learn to do each of
them better all of these skills will
still be useful for as long as we have
jobs there are skills that you can
practice and hone while working as a
software developer or learning to be a
software developer regardless of your
seniority and tex
stack but even beyond that I want to say
programming itself is more than just
coding and maybe this section should be
titled something more along the lines of
programming can be a suet of coding and
if I'm being very reductionist and I I
want to be clear very reductionist I see
sort of two categories of programmers
there's solution copiers and there's
problem solvers solution copier is not
exclusively about using copypaste
Solutions it's about using copypaste
solutions for copypaste problems without
examination as a clarification there are
a lot of people who primarily sort of
copy and paste code and solve a
ridiculous amount of problems they could
be like a scrappy solo startup right and
they are copy pasting because they don't
have an engineer uh you know a legion of
Engineers to write a bunch of code they
need to take the solutions that are
available and ship quickly and iterate
or maybe they're a non-programmer using
Excel and copy basted Python scripts to
power some ridiculous real estate Empire
I don't know the point is I'm not
actually talking about that group of
people here those people are still
problem solvers they're just focusing on
a different set of problems and a
different set of solutions the solution
copers they're not interested in how
things work just getting passed to the
next task they're sort of unaware of the
ways that different libraries and
language and tools can solve their
problems or might not solve their
problems they just copy paste the first
solution from a stack Overflow problem
or now maybe their favorite llm until CI
is green there's no concept of
considering the context that they're
that they're currently in but this isn't
just limited to technical problems like
we've been talking about it might be
that they're not interested at all how
their business works or how their makes
money or what their customers want right
and maybe that they've never considered
does the structure of our own
organization help us meet the goals and
desires that we're setting out to do
in contrast we have the problem solvers
these are curious people who try to
solve problems via understanding and I
think these skills will remain useful
even if we never write a single line of
code
again and this is sort of where I think
people are underestimating the skills
that they can once again can learn via
software development right and my point
here is that it it's possible to not
learn these and to not practice these
even if you've been writing code for a
long time so for example I think logic
iCal thinking is something that we can
practice while we're doing software
development we can practice decomposing
large problems into smaller ones we can
work on recognizing iterating and
solving issues for customers that
they're actually willing to pay for you
can get better at domain analysis right
understanding a problem set possible
solutions and then how to implement some
business logic or process to solve that
you can work on predicting edge cases or
failure modes for those processes you
learn how to trade-off management and
understand that there exists tradeoffs
that you need to manage then there's
pattern recognition which is useful all
around us and so each of these skills
seem to me at least like muscles that
you can train and get better at you can
use software development as a vehicle
for doing that training and all of these
skills are going to be useful once again
for as long as we have jobs to do same
with the soft skills that I mentioned in
the software
section let me give you an example sort
of ill illustrate this A Tale of Two
neovim if you will and I know some
people are already going to say using
neovim that's just a waste of time
that's okay that's fine if you don't
like neovim that's fine but I want to
give a parable sort of of two different
people using neovim uh it's not an
exhaustive list just just two examples
so the first person tries out neovim
because of some extrinsic reason and
they're hurried to get to Step One of
using neovim they don't take time to
read or understand or explore something
breaks in their config and they just
post on Reddit until someone posts or
with solution they might make an issue
with no reproduction steps and we've
seen this kind of person in every Dev
community and you can probably relate in
my opinion this person actually is
wasting their time with neovim which by
the way is totally okay we all like to
waste our time in different ways I like
playing stard to Valley with my wife and
we waste time together and it's really
nice Pac-Man users wouldn't understand
however there isn't any learning going
on through this neovim experience which
is bad if it characterizes every
interaction that you have with skills
that sort of are the culmination of your
field compare this to someone who's
enjoying using neovim they learn to
understand how to read documentation
they might learn a new programming
language they learn new idioms and apis
that can teach them about software
design when something breaks in their
configuration they learn how to read an
error message I know controversial in
2024 they learn to debug software
systems they learn about rolling back
about lock files they may even create a
PR to fix a problem
they build solutions for themselves and
are able to rapidly iterate on them
towards something that solves a real
world problem for them they're their own
customer this person has learned a lot
even if they end up with exactly the
same code AS person one both people
spend a lot of time on neovim uh and the
but the first one though was a solution
copier and the second a problem solver
the skills attitudes and perspectives
characterizing the problem solver are
helpful in many of other domains even if
AI takes overwriting software for them
forever and they never get to use a
modal text editor again which obviously
would be very said in the examples I
gave you can replace neovim with
whatever technology you want react spelt
rust hmx Excel whatever it doesn't
matter the pattern and the idea is the
same and my ultimate Point here is that
you get to choose how you're going to
tackle problems and the takeaways you'll
have from actually solving that problem
to move from copy pter to Giga Chad
Problem Solver as someone in my chat put
it largely revolves around you deciding
to start thinking and asking questions
today and that's pretty much it then you
make that same Choice tomorrow and the
day after that and the day after that
and then you just keep doing that in a
practical example in Practical terms of
something you could try to do this with
just build something for yourself that
solves a real problem that you have it's
okay if someone else has already built
it the point is that you're going to
build it for yourself to see if you can
solve this problem something difficult
when making products for other people
particularly in you know large
businesses or with a bunch of other
people working on the project it's very
hard to distinguish good feedback from
loud feedback it's common to have some
loud feedback that seems to overwhelm
and outweigh all of the other feedback
that you are getting so the nice thing
about building something for yourself by
yourself is you get to be that loud and
obnoxious user and then eventually
you'll get to decide if you've solved
your problem or not and if you didn't
that's okay you iterate as I tell my
three-year-old son it's okay to fail
that's part of how we learn the
important part is that we use our
roughness and our toughness to try again
and you can translate that to any age
appropriate way of saying that for
you in conclusion what I want to make
clear though is that I'm not saying
solution copiers are bad people or that
I don't like them instead I'm trying to
communicate that I would be a bit more
concerned if all the skills that I've
developed revolved around regurgitating
existing solutions that to me seems an
area that is more likely to be automated
by AI in some fashion and more quickly
than other areas of software
development I don't like giving advice
on the internet mostly because life is
much too complicated for someone to
explain their situation to me and then
it's much too complicated for me to
explain my advice to them through this
medium so I I generally don't give
advice but sort of despite this advice
for me like be curious pay attention
work hard don't be afraid to fail those
have never really led me astray thinking
this way once again in my opinion right
gives someone the best chance at success
regardless of how quickly and thoroughly
AI expands into other software Fields I
don't know what the future is going to
look like I'm just a regular mortal I
put my pants on two legs at a time but I
do think even discounting all the
arguments I've made throughout the video
right that if your current hypothesis is
that billions of new lines of code are
going to be generated it seems likely
that
truly understanding some things about
code now not everything not every
language not every framework not every
type system but just some things about
software itself that seems to me to be a
beneficial skill compared to any other
possible skills you might have or might
want to learn particularly if you like
learning about it and you want to get
really good at it I hope that this can
be encouraging to you to both learn and
work hard in your software Endeavors and
also some confidence that maybe even if
we never get to write code again that a
lot of what we're learning can be really
useful and transferred to other domains
let me know what you think let me know
if you like the video thanks everybody I
love you see you later